To adapt in an uncertain, changing world,
complex systems must integrate new information
while maintaining stability.
Too much destabilization prevents consistent learning;
too much reliance on past memory locks in outdated
patterns.
Biology solves this with an interplay of mechanisms
metaplasticity that tunes how much synapses change,
homeostasis that regulates the system around a set
point, inhibition,
and resets that enable forgetting.
The self-optimization model is a Hopfield network
with Hebbian learning and periodic resets
that already builds a memory of visited attractors
and enlarges the basin of the global
energy minimum,
making it a promising candidate to be enriched with
more of these biological features.